Today's דף daf is דף ס' daf samech 60. It is the
last דף daf of חזקת הבתים. Chazkas Habatim. So I don't know
if people are happy or going to be sad to see חזקת
הבתים Chazkas Habatim go, but חזקת הבתים Chazkas Habatim is definitely probably
the
most intensive of the פרקים prakim in בבא בתרא, Bava Basra, the
one that's classically learned in the ישיבות. Yeshivos. I think it's been
great and today we will be wrapping it up. So let's start
from the top of ס' עמוד א'. Samech Amud Aleph. We're now
dealing with a series of משניות Mishnayot that are less third פרק
perek משניות Mishnayot and more second פרק perek משניות. Mishnayot. It's sort
of interesting the shifting back and forth because so much about this
has been about the חזקה chazakah of demonstrating that you own it,
that you've been there for three years. We dealt with the חזקה
chazakah about taking possession and now we're dealing with a חזקה chazakah
more about the fact of like rights of use, things that have
to do with neighbors and if I'm doing certain types of things
and they invade your space or somehow possibly affect you or actually
are directly using your space and is your silence an acquiescence that
is sort of waiving me and giving me those rights and those
types of issues. So our משנה Mishnah spoke about the fact that
you've got a shared courtyard amongst houses and that you are what
are you allowed and not allowed to do. So in particular what
you're not allowed to do is to open up a house into
it, even let's say a house from another courtyard, let's say it's
somehow the back of that house was facing this courtyard and you
were to open up a back door or something of that nature
which would increase the foot traffic through the courtyard. Obviously that would
be clear, the members of the courtyard could say you don't have
a right to be increasing the foot traffic. Okay, but what it
does say you can do is or if you let's say built
a addition onto your house and you built a second story, you
cannot create a door, maybe with a I assume with a ladder
or something, exterior steps, but you cannot create a have a second
story and have a new door going into the courtyard. But what
you are allowed to do it says,
the end of the משנה Mishnah said what you can do is
אלא אם רצה בונה את החדר לפנים מביתו בונה עלייה על גבי
ביתו ופותחה לתוך ביתו. Ella im ratzah boneh et hachedar liphnim mibeito
boneh aliyah al gabei beito uphotchah letoch beito. You can build an
addition behind your house and then build a second story on top
of the addition and then have the second story go into the
addition of your house. Like it's not clear why that makes things
any better. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Top
of ס' עמוד א'. Samech Amud Aleph. לקח בית בחצר אחרת ופתחה
לחצר השותפין. Lakach bayis bechatzer acheres uphotchah lechatzer shutaphin. If you bought
a house in another courtyard you can't have it directly open into
this courtyard. It's not exactly clear what the sort of layout is
so that a house from another courtyard can open up into this.
The easiest scenario I can imagine is what I described is that
the back of the house
faces your courtyard, the front opens up into another. Don't put a
back door into that house and now you will allow create new
access into this courtyard. Okay, so that's something of that nature. So
מאי טעמא, mai taama, what's the reason? asks the גמרא. Gemara. מפני
שמרבה עליהם את הדרך mipnei shemarbeh aleihem es haderech because you increase
the foot traffic. It's funny the phrase מרבה עליהם את הדרך marbeh
aleihem es haderech to me makes it sound like you're increasing the
you're making them go out of the way. Actually you're not making
them go out of the way at all, you're making it more
convenient for at least the people of the house. No, the problem
is is that you're increasing the foot traffic,
the דריכת הרגל drichas haregel if you would in the in this
courtyard. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אימא סיפא, eima seifa, okay,
then let's look at the end of
the
משנה. Mishnah. אלא אם רצה בונה את החדר לפנים מביתו ובונה עלייה
על גבי ביתו. Ella im ratzah boneh es hachedar liphnim mibeito uvoneh
aliyah al gabei beito.
But if you want to, here's what you can do. Build a
back addition to the house in the back and then build a
second story on top of that back addition. So who cares? Every
whoever's going to be moving into that second story is going to
go
then
down here and then through your house and then out the door.
Wonderful, there's still going to be more people in the courtyard, they're
just all going to use the same door. So why does that
make it any better? It makes it
worse for you that you have to deal with out your you're
allowed to do whatever you want. The problem is you how you
compromising the people in the courtyard. So why does but why is
this any better? So you make these people have to travel more,
you make your house more traffic, but in the end there's still
going to be more people going through the courtyard. So let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says.
So this is not a second door, this is you keep the
same door.
Right, exactly.
So it sounds like exactly that that the issue is how much.
is opening a new door, right? But the גמרא Gemara says something
like, why should that matter if in the end you're going to
be putting tenants over there? So the גמרא Gemara says, so והלוא,
ve-halo, so the גמרא Gemara says והלוא מרבה עליו את הדרך, ve-halo
marbe alav et haderech,
aren't you sort of increasing the foot traffic? Now again, I have
to tell you, I'm reading this like the רשב"ם Rashbam that מרבה
עליו את הדרך marbe alav et haderech means increasing the foot traffic.
But it's an interesting shift here from the plural to the singular.
If מרבה עליהם marbe aleihem means means the members of the courtyard,
then this also should have been מרבה עליהם את הדרך. marbe aleihem
et haderech. It sounds like we're talking about the extra people that
you're lodging, but then it doesn't make any sense. So I don't
know, I'm going to go with the רשב"ם. Rashbam. If somebody has
a better read on well on I'd be welcome to hear it.
But anyway, we're going to read it like the רשב"ם. Rashbam. What
difference does it make, aren't you still increasing the foot traffic in
the courtyard? אמר רב הונא Amar Rav Huna no, מאי חדר שחילקו
בשנים? mai cheder shechilko bishnayim? ומאי עלייה? עלייה אפתא. u-mai aliyah? aliyah
aftai.
So he says no, no. He says you misunderstood it. When it
says that you can build a back room, it doesn't really mean
that you can build a back room. You're not allowed to build
a back room because let's say you're going to build a back
addition and what just happened here? You're going to build a back
addition and you're going to put, you know, rent out this space.
Well then you're increasing the, you know, the foot traffic and you're
increasing the, you know, tenants of the courtyard, the residents of the
courtyard. No, no. What you can do is if you have a
big house, then you're allowed to divide your house into two. And
then you are allowed to put tenants here. What's the difference? Because
he says look, let's say you didn't divide your house into two.
In theory, there's no rule in the courtyard about how many guests
you're allowed to have. Let's say I just decide to tell my
extended family, my aunts and uncles and cousins, come on over, move
in with me, spend the next six months visiting me. The people
nobody in the courtyard can say hey, that's not fair, there's going
to be a lot of foot traffic. I'm allowed to have whatever
whoever whatever guests I want, however many guests I want in my
house. Nobody can tell me I can't. What I'm not allowed to
do is to introduce new residents into the courtyard. So what the
גמרא Gemara is saying is that if this is your whole house
and you could have packed that with your family and with your
guests, then you could also just build a wall in the house
and, you know, rent out the space because you're not really because
like hypothetically in theory those could have just been guests. But what
you can't do is you can't build an addition for the sake
of creating a new rental space or build a second story. That's
actually considered not like you're theoretically welcoming guests into your house, right?
That's actually seen as though you are actually creating new residents of
the courtyard.
Does it have to do with
intention?
Well, what it has to do with is not intention because actually
when you make a division you're doing it specifically for the purpose
of renting out that space. What it has to do with is
how halakhically and again, I think this is an interesting solution, it
wouldn't have been the solution I would have guessed. Let's say we
understand that on the one hand we can't stop you from having
as many guests as you want in your house, but what we
can do is you can't do things that are bringing new residents
into the courtyard. So so what do you mean by resident, right?
What what's the line between residents and guests? Okay. So what I
would have said is that the difference would have been is like
are you charging them rent? Right? Like, you know, you don't have
to prove that they're your friends or your family to be allowed
to have them visit you, but if they're people that actually you're
charging them rent and they have legal rights to be there or
whatever, like that would be the difference. That's what I would have
said. The way the גמרא Gemara seems to be answering the difference
is whether you have built an addition for them or you know
added on space, built a second story, built a back space, or
if you've just subdivided your own house. Like let's say I've got
a lot of kids and I want to put up a lot
of walls and subdivide my house. I'm allowed to subdivide my house.
So the גמרא Gemara seems to say, and I don't know if
this is פשט pshat in the משנה, Mishna, that the divide the
determinant factor is subdivision is okay whereas new additions for the sake
of like if it's new additions for my own family that would
be presumably okay. But new additions for the sake of like, you
know, having income or resident or renting it out, right, would not
be good. Now what I would have said the פשט pshat in
the משנה Mishna take your comments in a minute. What I would
have said the פשט pshat in the משנה Mishna is, is the
משנה Mishna seems to be a more simple פשט. pshat. The משנה
Mishna seems to say the way we're going to measure that is
whether you're is whether you're creating new doors or not, new doorways.
That seems to be the concern of the משנה, Mishna, right? So
so if you want to create a back like a back space
and a new עלייה aliyah and everybody's still going to use that
one door, as long as you have the same number of doors
we're not we're not going to judge how you're using how you're
using your house. Because it's because it's because it's like it's somewhat
arbitrary, but it's a it's a simple legal way of measuring. Okay.
Yeah, but it leads to me,
and you know, and it's easier because because the reality is is
that people tend not to rent out their space if you don't
have a separate entrance, right? If I'm subdividing whatever, who how you
know, the natural thing is
So the פשט pshat of the משנה mishna seems to be a
simple measure of are you adding doors. If you're adding doors, then
you're then it's seen as increasing the potential for traffic. If you're
not, of course it's possible either way, you know, but if you're
not, then it's not. The גמרא Gemara says it's a question of
creating an addition to your house or subdividing your house. You could
have said the difference was are you renting the space or not
renting the space. Okay, but those are let me just read the
last line and then I'll take the questions. So אמר רב הונא
Amar Rav Huna מאי חדר שחלקו לשנים, mai cheder shechilko lishnayim, you
divide, you subdivided, that's allowed. You didn't add an addition, you subdivided.
ומאי עלייה, Umai aliyah, what does it mean when it says you
can build a second story? It doesn't literally mean build a second
story, it means אפתיא aftaya which apparently according to the רשב״ם Rashbam
means it's sort of like a subdivision height-wise. So like a loft,
actually that would be a good thing, like you know those big
lofts, right? So they've got like it's all under, like it's not
literal, it's basically you've got a high ceiling and you subdivide it
height-wise rather than actually building a second story. So subdivision is okay,
a new construction project is not okay. Now, could I do a
new construction project if I just ברוך השם Baruch Hashem have a
growing family? Am I only not to do a new addition if
it's like no, that's and always a big question, am I allowed
to make additions to my house, right? You know, so that's like
left a very, you know, open-ended. Yeah.
Okay, but let's say you take your house, you move out, and
you subdivide it, but now you make it into a hotel. Can
you do it? And everyone goes out the front door.
According to the רשב״ם Rashbam you can. That's the way he's reading
the גמרא. Gemara. It's all determined by whether you're actually any subdividing,
whatever your intent is okay, any addition is not okay.
But that doesn't make much sense. I understand. I mean, now 15
more people going out.
I understand, and I don't think it's also פשט pshat of the
משנה. mishna. No. I think פשט pshat of the משנה mishna is
how many doors do you have?
Rabbi, that wouldn't also make sense according to either.
If I have a hotel, if I really subdivided it in a
way that I have like a common lobby and then everyone goes
out the front door, right? Right, it's true. I assume that wasn't
as common. I assume you didn't have bed and breakfasts, you had
more like really renting of a property. Yes.
On that note piece, wouldn't they say you can't do business in
the חצר? chatzer?
Oh, oh, that's a nice point too, like like what's the line
between I'm renting out my house and I'm actually I have a
business here, I have a hotel. Right, that's a good point, like
that could be אסור. assur. If I can't open up a school
because I'm bringing all this traffic in. Yeah, that's a nice point.
Right.
If the house is
subdivided, then I would think there's an argument that the size of
the house gives the other people in the חצר chatzer some idea
of the maximum capacity that can be in that space.
Right, right, so that's why subdivision is allowed. So you're say yeah
right, but then I see. So that's a good point, so that
the size is basically is just going to wind up being a
limit on total capacity. Yeah.
Is if these types of structural definitions are common sense? If you
subdivide a large apartment on the Upper West Side and put six
guys in there instead of three, it's still three-bedroom apartment. You have
a junior four, what's the difference between a junior four and a
two-bedroom apartment? A closet. You put a closet it's an additional room
you have two-bedroom where the rent goes up. Structural features like doorways
it's it's very ancient.
Okay, great, great. Okay, let's look at the yeah, one last thing.
And if you could just say the עליהם. aleichem.
Oh, the עליהם aleichem is the second one too. עליהם aleichem oh
עליו alav and עליהם. aleichem. Okay, but anyway, at least it's more
consistent with the רשב״ם. Rashbam. Okay, thank you for that. Okay, let's
look at the next משנה. mishna. לא יפתח אדם לחצר השותפין פתח
כנגד פתח וחלון כנגד חלון. Lo yiftach adam lachatzar hashutafin petach keneged
petach vechalon keneged chalon.
So interestingly, although the previous משנה mishna said you're not allowed to
open up a window that hadn't been there, right? Because you're now
you're now making the space less private. But here it sounds like
it's a case where you do have a right to open up
windows. The רשב״ם Rashbam says you have a חזקה, chazaka, so it's
not exactly clear like or maybe somehow whatever the courtyard has agreed
that people can open up new windows or everybody has a right
to have two windows facing the courtyard. So fundamentally, there is a
right to have windows open to create a window. But even within
that, you are not allowed to have a window directly facing another
window as opposed to like every single apartment building in Manhattan, right,
where you can look straight into the next person's place. But here,
no. You're allowed even in cases where you're allowed windows into the
courtyard, you are not allowed them directly facing other windows of your
neighbor. פתח Petach and similarly doorways directly facing other doorways, which is
interesting because you would think by the time somebody gets around to
opening their door, right, they're ready to leave the house, like what
are but you know why do they have to maintain privacy? But
there might be people behind them in the door, but normally, you
know, you open, your body is filling up the doorway, you wouldn't
have thought it's as much of a privacy concern.
You look into the person's house.
I understand, right, a little bit. Right. So therefore, so even that
you can't do. the חלון כנגד חלון. chalon k'neged chalon. Okay, פתח
כנגד פתח ולא חלון כנגד חלון. petach k'neged petach v'lo chalon k'neged
chalon. היה קטן לא יעשנו גדול. Haya katan lo ya'asenu gadol.
If you had a small doorway, you can't make it into a
big doorway. Now, why not? Like, again, what's the concern here? You're
going to allow for there to be more inhabitants in the house?
Not exactly clear. אחד לא יעשנו שנים. Echad lo ya'asenu shnayim. One
doorway, don't make it into two. אבל פותח הוא לרשות הרבים Aval
poteach hu l'reshut harabim פתח כנגד פתח וחלון כנגד חלון. petach k'neged
petach v'chalon k'neged chalon. Let's say your, you know, your house is
directly opens up into the רשות הרבים reshut harabim and across the
street, there's another house that opens into the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim.
Then you can make a doorway facing a doorway and a window
facing a window for the obvious reason that there's a lot of
foot traffic there on the רשות הרבים reshut harabim anyway. So people
would be able to look into anybody's doorway or window. So it
doesn't matter if you add one more person on the other side
of the street. The reality though is, of course, it does matter
because of nighttime, you know, when people aren't concerned about the רשות
הרבים reshut harabim and then they, you know, in New York it
matters because of the windows that are high up. You can't see
from the רשות הרבים reshut harabim the high-up windows, but you have
these two parallel buildings, you know, ten stories high and you still
see straight into somebody's apartment. But okay, but in this case, when
we're dealing with one story and presumably everybody went to sleep at
night and you didn't have electric lighting, it was once it was
already
open to רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, you're not really doing anything more
by having another house across the street that directly faces it. היה
קטן עושה אותו גדול, Haya katan oseh oto gadol, אחד עושה אותו
שנים. echad oseh oto shnayim. Similarly, you can make the doorways bigger
or divide them into two once we deal with רשות הרבים. reshut
harabim. Those concerns don't exist. Not exactly clear what the concerns are
at the end. We'll see in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's look at
the גמרא. Gemara. מנא הני מילי? Mena hani mili? Where's this from?
אמר רבי יוחנן דאמר קרא, Amar Rabbi Yochanan d'amar kra, וישא בלעם
את עיניו וירא ישראל שוכן לשבטיו. Vayisa Bilam et einav vayar Yisrael
shochen lishvatav. Oh, this was what so this is something I think
that they teach a lot in the day schools because it's a
very beautiful idea, right? It says Bilam lifted up his eyes and
he saw Israel dwelling according to their tribes and he said מה
טובו אהליך יעקב. Ma tovu ohalecha Yaakov. How great are your tents,
O Jacob. So what was he responding to? Like what, that we
know how to build nice tents? Like, you know, what was that
praise about? So here's the classic rabbinic take on this: מה ראה?
Ma ra? What did he see? ראה שאין פתחי אהליהם מכוונים זה
לזה. Ra she'ein pitchei ohaleihem mechovanim zeh lazeh.
He saw that their doorways did not open facing one another, that
they arranged their homes in a way that protected one another's privacies.
And that's מה טובו אהליך יעקב. Ma tovu ohalecha Yaakov. אמר ראויים
הללו שתשרה עליהם שכינה. Amar reuyim halalu shetishreh aleihem Shechina. Oh, now
you see that that makes sense why the divine presence is fit
to dwell upon these people. תוספות Tosafot says that it picks up
on the end of the פסוק pasuk because it says ותהי עליו
רוח אלקים. Vatehi alav ruach Elokim. Like, he had the divine presence
dwell on him, you know, maybe when he saw this and was
inspired, so he saw that this was somehow connected, you know, to
that sense of the divine presence. It's interesting, I hadn't really fully
unpacked that but, you know, what is that? Does that have to
do with the fact of like the צלם אלקים tzelem Elokim respecting
somebody's somehow
privacy, צניעות tzniut and so on with this idea of תשרה עליהם
שכינה. tishreh aleihem Shechina. If somebody can, you know, other than it's
a beautiful thing, so תשרה עליהם שכינה. tishreh aleihem Shechina. You could
say he saw they were giving צדקה, tzedakah, ראוי שתשרה. rauy shetishreh.
I'm wondering if there's a more direct connection with this concept here
about like respecting privacy.
It's היזק ראיה. Hezek re'iah.
It's היזק ראיה, Hezek re'iah, right? Exactly, exactly, exactly. Okay. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: היה קטן ולא יעשנו גדול. Haya
katan v'lo ya'asenu gadol.
I mean, of course, the divine house where the שכינה Shechina is
שורה shora in the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash is obviously very well
protected, right? In the sense of that access to the divine presence,
right? You have the פרוכת, parochet, you have, you know, the קודש,
kodesh, the קודש קדשים kodesh kodashim and all of that. So there
might be an element of that going here. But anyway, but this
real sense about how beautiful it was that it was arranged in
a way to respect everybody's privacy.
How every tent was ראוי rauy to be to be the שכינה.
Shechina. Because oh, that's a nice idea.
That you see the tent as like the place where the שכינה
Shechina dwells because the שכינה Shechina is in an אהל, ohel, like
אהל מועד. ohel moed. Ah, there you go, very nice. היה קטן
לא יעשנו גדול. Haya katan lo ya'asenu gadol. סבר רבה בר בר
חנה למימר, Savar Rabbah Bar Bar Chana l'meimar, בר ד' לא לישויה
בר תמניא. bar dalet lo lishaveih bar tamnya. Because what's the problem?
It's what does it mean making it a bigger opening? It's still
one opening, why is that impacting you? Like how does that hurt
you that my doorway is bigger? So he says, no, here's the
problem. If you had an opening
that was a four אמה amah opening, don't turn it into an
eight
אמה amah opening because שקא תמניא בחצר. shaka tamnya b'chatzer. So here's
a little pop quiz everybody: who remembers going back many דפים dapim
to a previous פרק, perek, the הלכה halacha that here we have
houses opening up into a חצר chatzer
and
we have houses opening up into a חצר chatzer and then we're
going to divide the חצר, chatzer, and the question is: how much
do you get? So we divided according to the number of houses.
But before we divided according to the number of houses, we count
But the minimum size of a doorway, right,
is four אמות. amos. So if you only had a four אמות
amos doorway, you would get this, and everybody would get their doorway,
and then you would divide the rest. But if I go ahead
and I make it into an eight אמה amah doorway, I'm going
to get a bigger piece of that חצר chatzer if we ever
wind up dividing it, or even if we don't divide it. Like
I have a claim, a more of a personal claim to that
space in the חצר. chatzer. So he says the problem here is
not a היזק ראייה hezek re'iyah problem. The problem here is that
by making a bigger doorway, you're claiming rights to a larger piece
of the חצר. chatzer. Okay, so that's the claim. בר ארבע לא
לישווי בר תמניא דקשקל תמניא בחצר, bar arba lo lishavei bar tamnaya
de'kashakal tamnaya be'chatzer, because now you're going to get a,
not four by four, but eight by four in the
חצר. chatzer. אבל בר תרתי לישווי בר ארבע שפיר דמי. aval bar
tartei lishavei bar arba shapir dami. But let's say this had been
a very small doorway of only two אמות. amos. So the point
is so I get four אמות amos in, but it's always with
a minimum width of four אמות. amos. So even if my door
is only two, in that scenario I would have gotten four by
four anyway. You always get a minimum width of four. It's a
minimum of four and a maximum of the width of your doorway.
So he said in this case, if you started with two and
you opened it to four, you're not claiming any more space. You're
already entitled to four by four.
And the door's not supposed to be bigger than four though, right?
No, whatever the starting size of the door is, is fine. Right.
But he said the amount you get in the courtyard is the
width of the door by four אמות. amos. But the minimum is
four by four. So he says if it started as four and
you grow it, you're seizing a bigger part of the courtyard. But
if it started as two, you're already entitled to four by four,
so you can open it up to four. Okay, so he thought
that would be okay. שפיר דמי. shapir dami. אמר ליה רבא, amlei
Rava, so רבא Rava said back to him, מצי אמר ליה בפתחא
זוטא מצינא לאיצטנויי מינך בפתחא רבא לא מצינא לאיצטנויי מינך. mati amlei
be'picha zutra matzina litzenuyei minach be'picha raba lo matzina litzenuyei minach. No,
no, no. I could, when you had a doorway that was narrow,
it gave me, when I was doing stuff in the courtyard, more
privacy. Like because I knew that, I don't know, I knew that
I could do something over here and you wouldn't see it because
you would be coming out of a narrow doorway. And now that
you've given yourself a larger doorway, you might be standing over here
and seeing something that otherwise I would have had more privacy to
do. So even though you already are going in and out of
the courtyard, you're just widening your door, right, when you actually go
out into the courtyard I'll see you and I won't be doing
my private stuff. But if I'm standing in my doorway, right, I
have some pretty good, I can look around and see what people
are doing. So if I have a wider doorway, it allows me
to see places I couldn't have seen before, and therefore you can
say you are compromising the degree of privacy that was available in
the courtyard. Okay, so it doesn't matter.
That's why even in the end they only get four אמות amos
in.
Right, but that's besides, what he's saying this has nothing to do,
and this read is of course a much better read of the
משנה mishna because the משנה mishna does not seem to be about
property rights. The משנה mishna seems to be about the sense about
היזק ראייה, hezek re'iyah, right?
So it would be like four to five?
Exactly. So that's what רבא Rava is saying. I don't care if
you go two to three, three to four, four to five. Any
widening is somewhat increasing,
decreasing people's degree of privacy of the courtyard. Sure you can go
out into the courtyard, but then I know you're out there. My
concern is when you're standing in the doorway, you've opened your doorway
a crack and you're looking out into the courtyard and I don't
know that you're doing it. So now you've increased your visibility, your
ability to look into the courtyard, yes.
And so then for that, then wouldn't there be some prohibition or
regulation about the number of windows?
There is, and that was the previous משנה. mishna. That's why the
previous משנה mishna said you can't open up a new window into
the courtyard. Oh, I didn't catch that. Okay, so yes, yesterday's משנה
mishna across from each. No, no, so that's what I said. Yesterday's
משנה mishna says you can't open up a new window at all
into the courtyard. This משנה mishna is assuming that we have, maybe
we're just building new construction, I don't know. Okay, but assuming that
we've agreed that we can have a certain number of windows, and
even within there, they can't be facing one another. Okay, but yes,
but if we already have a given setup, you can't open up
a new window without permission and you can't even, what this משנה
mishna is saying is widen a doorway without permission. It's right, opening
a window is even worse, but it's the same idea. Okay. So
let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אחד
לא יעשנו שנים. echad lo ya'asenu shnayim. Similarly, if you have one
doorway, don't turn it into two. סבר רמי בר חמא, savar Rami
bar Chama, so it's going to be the same issue. רמי בר
חמא Rami bar Chama thought this was about property rights. רמי בר
חמא Rami bar Chama thought to say, בר ארבע לא לישווי תרי
בני תרתי תרתי דקשקל תמני בחצר. bar arba lo lishavei trei benei
tartei tartei de'kashakal tamnei be'chatzer. If you actually had a doorway
that was four,
it was four, but you're not allowed to do is turn it
into two doorways of two. Right? Why can you not turn it
into two doors of two? Because for every door you're entitled to
four-by-four in the חצר. chatzer. So when you had a door of
four, you got four-by-four. If you have two doors of two, you're
going to get two times four-by-four. So again, he thinks the whole
thing is property rights based on doorways. Okay, so therefore, so that's
what he said. רמי בר חמא, Rami bar Chama, if you had
an eight foot doorway, eight אמה amah doorway, ושוייה בני ארבע ארבע,
v'shavyei benei arba arba, then you can't do two doorways of four
because if you had an eight foot doorway, an eight אמה amah
doorway, you'd have gotten eight-by-four. Now that it's two fours, you get
four-by-four times two, which is the same as eight-by-four. Okay, so you're
not getting any more property rights. אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei Rava,
so רבא Rava again pushed back. He says that is not פשט
peshat in the משנה. Mishna.
מצי אמר ליה, Matzi amar lei, בחד פיתחא מצינא אצנועי מינך, bechad
pitcha matzina itznu'ei minach, בתרי פיתחי לא מצינא אצנועי מינך. bitrei pitchi
la matzina itznu'ei minach. No, if you had one big doorway, I
knew when your door was open, right, and you know, it's hard
to hide behind, you know, to peek out, you know, you got
one big doorway. Anyway, there's actually less privacy with two smaller doorways
than with one big one because I could see one door and
think it's closed and you're actually, you could have opened up the
other door, you know, and are peeking out there and it's true,
like, you know, there's a great, you know, it is more, if
I'm in the house and I have two separate doorways, it's easier
for me to peek out and see what's going on than if
I've got one big doorway. Okay, so it's all a privacy issue.
אבל פותח לרשות הרבים פתח כנגד פתח, Aval poteach l'reshut harabim petach
keneged petach,
but if you're opening into רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, then none of
these problems exist because דאמר ליה, d'amar lei, as the גמרא Gemara
says, because the other guy can say to you, the guy who
wants to open up the windows or the doors or whatever, says
סוף סוף הבייתא אצנועי מיניה רשות הרבים. sof sof habayita itznu'ei minei
reshut harabim. You don't have, you can't be assuming any privacy because
you've got a רשות הרבים reshut harabim in front of your house.
So I'm not doing anything to decrease your privacy. Plus as we
said nowadays it's not exactly true because of people do things at
night in their homes and so on where there's not really foot
traffic. Anyway, let's take a look at the next משנה. Mishna. אין
עושין חלל תחת רשות הרבים, Ein osin chalal tachat reshut harabim, this
is something that was quoted earlier. This again, this also's like, we're
just jumping, seems to be from like topic to topic. I mean
they are loosely related, but moving from a normal חזקה chazakah of
three years to going back to second פרק Perek issues about compromising
people's privacy in a חצר. chatzer. Now we're going to do with
doing things in רשות הרבים reshut harabim that are potentially, you know,
like, threatening to the safety of the people of רשות הרבים, reshut
harabim, a different type of a concern. אין עושין חלל תחת רשות
הרבים. Ein osin chalal tachat reshut harabim. I cannot go ahead and
dig a tunnel under רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. I don't know who
sold me the property rights to that tunnel underneath רשות הרבים, reshut
harabim, but let's even say I have those property rights, I can't
dig that tunnel because then the top is going to collapse and
I'm creating a threat to the safety of רשות הרבים. reshut harabim.
Okay, בור שיח ומערות, bor shich ve'mearot, and similarly you cannot go
ahead and dig these types of wells or canals or whatever, cisterns
in רשות הרבים reshut harabim
because you're creating a potential hazard. I mean, obviously, if the רבים
rabim hired you to make a nice cistern there so people can
get a drink, of course you're allowed, but for whatever reason just
on your own even if you had property rights you cannot do
this because you are creating this hazard. רבי אליעזר מתיר כדי שתהא
עגלה מהלכת וטעונה אבנים. Rabbi Eliezer matir kedei shetehei agalah mehalechet utuna
avanim. He says, he allows it. By the way, the בור שיח
ומערות bor shich ve'mearot is not clear if that means like just
a straight cistern directly in רשות הרבים reshut harabim or does it
mean I'm digging my own cistern, you know, here I am in
my property and I'm digging my, you know, whatever, and I'm digging
my cistern, and in order and here's the רשות הרבים, reshut harabim,
and because the water's drying up in order to get access, right,
I am, you know, continuing to dig under רשות הרבים, reshut harabim,
you know, to get access for my, for my בור bor that's
in my property. Okay, so it could be that's the continuation of
the previous discussion. It's not just סתם stam building a cistern in
רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. I'm digging in my property, but in order
to dig it, I'm going under רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Okay, so
the basic point is don't dig under רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. רבי
אליעזר מתיר Rabbi Eliezer matir כדי שתהא עגלה מהלכת וטעונה אבנים. kedei
shetehei agalah mehalechet utuna avanim. He says
if you have it built that the top is so strong that
even if, you know, a wagon carrying boulders, you know, has a
three-ton weight, you know, what's it called, weight tolerance or whatever,
you know, you can have a wagon with boulders go over and
it would not break the, you know, the ceiling of the tunnel,
then you're fine, then you are protecting the safety of רשות הרבים.
reshut harabim.
How do you test that?
I guess,
I guess you actually have the wagon go over. They weigh, they
step a weight. Oh
no, no, but we're saying is you would have to, you can
weigh the truck, but then you'd have to have it go over
to see. They knew engineering. Okay. They would know, it was just.
Anyway, but the debate is, as the גמרא Gemara elsewhere says that
the debate is whether it's all very nice that right now it's
totally safe, but who's in charge of making sure that it stays
that way? You know, and since nobody is in charge of making
sure that it stays that way, one year, two years, five years,
eventually there're going to be problems. There're going to be cracks and
fissures and then it will be a problem. So you don't create
it to begin with. That seems to be the debate. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this: אין מוציאין זיזין וגסטראות לרשות הרבים.
Ain motzin zizin vegustra'ot li-reshut harabim.
Now, if you have your house and it borders on רשות הרבים,
reshut harabim, that's the tie-in from the previous משנה. Mishnah. The previous
משנה Mishnah had the houses directly opening to רשות הרבים. reshut harabim.
So you cannot have these protrusions coming out of the walls of
your house or of your let's say a wall around your yard
into רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, which they would do sometimes. You know,
you have a little beam coming out and you'd use it to
hang things on, but obviously you can't have that going into the
street because that's a hazard. Okay, so אלא אם רצה. Ella im
ratzah. So let's say you but you want to do that. You
want a wall that has some exterior protrusions because those were functional
in some way. So what would you do? כונס לתוך שלו ומוציא.
Kones letokh shelo umotzi. Fine, go three feet or five feet into
your back from your boundary line, build your wall not right up
against the boundary line and then have the protrusions still within your
yard, not going into the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. All right, so
לקח חצר ובה זיזין וגסטראות. Lakach chatzer uvah zizin vegustra'ot.
Let's say I bought a courtyard, right? I mean now we switch
from a house to a courtyard, whatever, but and the wall around
the courtyard already has protrusions. And the courtyard was opened to רשות
הרבים. reshut harabim. So then what what happens here? Like nobody knows.
Is it that this person put the stuff in רשות הרבים reshut
harabim and nobody ever complained and they're here illegitimately and you have
to cut them down, these protrusions? Or maybe the courtyard initially built
the wall a little bit inset and the protrusions are actually in
the courtyard space and not the רשות הרבים reshut harabim space. So
in that case what already exists and you don't really know what
the story is, so in that case the הלכה halakha is
הרי זו בחזקתה. Harei zu be-chezkhatah.
You can assume that it's all fine. Now, the רשב"ם Rashbam says
that's only if you're the purchaser. If basically I'm the original person
who bought the who created the courtyard and now you're the רשות
הרבים reshut harabim people, you are the committee that has been appointed
by the rest of the community and you're saying your things are
going into the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. I can't say, 'well, it's
been here for the last, you know, couple years, nobody's complained, so
it must be okay'. Now, he says that you could say why
not? That's a חזקה, chazakah, three years, nobody's complained or whatever. The
רשב"ם Rashbam at least claims there's no גמרא Gemara on this, but
he at least claims no. Then you have the burden of proof.
You've got stuff that right now is right facing רשות הרבים. reshut
harabim. You're going to have to produce some direct evidence that this
is within your boundary line. But if somebody bought it who was
not the person who created it, in that case we assume that
since it's there, it's there legitimately. So it's funny why we do
why we don't assume that like I could go by a חזקה
chazakah three years. If nobody's complained in three years, why doesn't that
evidence, you know, that I must have it legitimately? It's not spelled
out in the משנה. Mishnah. That's what the רשב"ם Rashbam claims. Yes,
Jenna. You mean you
would be the one to complain? We're back to some stories in
גמרא. Gemara. It could be anybody could complain, right? So yeah, you
could say maybe nobody complains because it's not the רבים, rabim, but
the גמרא Gemara is really going to sort of say... the גמרא
Gemara sort of assumes the opposite, that anybody can complain but nobody
can be מוחל. mochel. Like in order to assume that the רבים
rabim is מוחל, mochel, you really would need the whole רבים rabim
to be acting in concert to be saying they're okay, which they
could do, right? They had representation, right? שבעה טובי העיר Shiva tuvei
ha-ir whatever. But but you can't just assume like that the silence
of the רבים rabim and maybe that's why the רשב"ם Rashbam says
there's no חזקה. chazakah. As a general rule, you can't assume that
the silence of the רבים rabim is a מחילה mechilah because who
are the רבים rabim to be מוחל? mochel? Like you would need
them all acting in concert. But any one of them can say
you're compromising my my right, you know, you're compromising my my ability
to use the road.
Yes, and is that precisely the רשב"ם's Rashbam's point in his last
words in that דיבור המתחיל? dibur hamat-chil? דהכל בני רשות הרבים מצי
למחויי לגבי דמחולי? de-hakol bnei reshut harabim matzi limchuyei legabei de-machulei? Yes,
that's his point.
Oh yeah, so he says that explicitly. I'd forgotten that. Yeah, exactly.
So right, so to get them to actually give me rights, they'd
have to all be acting in concert.
Not the silent
majority.
Exactly. So
therefore, but if I bought the חצר, chatzer, I can assume that
the arrangements were done correctly. And maybe this whole thing was was
done inset into the into the yard. Let's look at the גמרא.
Gemara. ורבנן, Ve-rabbanan, why do the Rabbis say that it's not enough
that you have a strong ceiling on top of this תנור? tannur?
זימנין דמיפחית ולאו אדעתיה, Zimnin demifchit velav adateih, because sometimes it'll crack
and nobody's paying attention. Okay, אין מוציאין זיזין וגסטראות. Ain motzin zizin
vegustra'ot. Now we're now we're going to go to the protrusions. And
we're going to have some interesting stories. רבי ינאי הוה ליה זיזא
דהוה נפיק למבואה. Rabbi Yannai hava lei ziza de-hava nafik lemavoeh. Rabbi
Yannai had a protrusion from his wall that entered into a מבוי.
mavoy. A מבוי, mavoy, the חצר chatzer are the courtyard, right? So
you imagine that we've got these like these like little yards, right,
that maybe have a few houses opening, and each one of these
yards and these and these yards, okay, and all these have these
houses, whatever, and what whatever, and they open up into a מבוי.
mavoy. A מבוי mavoy is an alley, okay, or like a side
street. And then the מבוי mavoy here, the מבואות mavo'ot open into
the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. So you've got all these like מבואות,
mavois, right, and then the courtyards open to the מבואות mavois into
the רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. So he had here in his courtyard
or his house, he had these protrusions and they were going into
the מבוי. mavoi. That's the story. All right. So, which you're not
supposed to.
Yes. Is there a difference between a מבואה mivoah and a מבוי?
mavoi?
Oh yeah? So a מבוי mavoi is like... I've not seen it
in the גמרא. Gemara. What's a מבואה?
mivoah? מבואה mivoah is like the entrance hall kind of.
Aha. And a מבוי mavoi is an alley, right? But but but
a side street is not a מבוי, mavoi, is it? A מבוי
mavoi is more like a back alley, right?
Back alley also sometimes מבוי סתום. mavoi satum.
מבוי סתום mavoi satum is a dead end, right. Yeah.
Okay.
מבואה mivoah can be in your house like the entry place.
Ah, oh interesting. Oh, oh I see. A vestibule. Vestibule. אכסדרה. achsadra.
Okay. Interesting. All right so let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. רבי אמי הוה ליה חזיזא דהוה מפיק למבוי. Rebbi Ammi
have lei haziza d'hava mafik l'mavoi. וההוא גברא נמי הוה ליה זיזא
דהוה מפיק לרשות הרבים. V'hahu gavra nami hava lei ziza d'hava mafik
l'reshus harabbim. And then there was some other guy and he had
his protrusion going into the רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. Okay. הוה קא
מעכבי ליה Hava ka me-akevei lei we'll read it with the parentheses
בני רשות הרבים. benei reshus harabbim. So the people of the רשות
הרבים, reshus harabbim, they started complaining to this other guy, not to
רבי אמי, Rebbi Ammi, and they said, "What are you doing? You
got protrusions in רשות הרבים." reshus harabbim. They called him to a
דין תורה. din Torah. Guess who they called him to a דין
תורה din Torah for? In front of רבי אמי. Rebbi Ammi. One
wonders who chose the venue here.
Okay. אתא לקמיה דרבי אמי. Ata l'kamei d'Rebbi Ammi. He came to
רבי אמי. Rebbi Ammi. What?
He should have recused himself.
Well, let's take a look. אמר ליה, Amar lei, רבי אמי Rebbi
Ammi said to him, זיל קוץ, zil kots, go cut away your
protrusion. אמר ליה, Amar lei, ומר נמי אית ליה, v'mar nami is
lei, but what do you mean? You've got protrusions into your alley.
So אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to him, דידי למבוי
מפיק, dididi l'mavoi mafik, mine goes into an alley, not a רשות
הרבים. reshus harabbim. בני מבוי מחלי גבאי. Benei mavoi machlin gabai. So
here there is a well-defined population, right? There are six courtyards, there
are three people in each courtyard, there are eighteen people that are
have use of this מבוי, mavoi, which is essentially like a private
street. So this מבוי mavoi everybody is quiet and that's
a מחילה. mechila. So actually it can work in a מבוי, mavoi,
it can't work in a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim where it's open
to anybody, it's a public not a private and then nobody is
able to be מוחל. mocheil. Okay. מחלי גבאי. Machlin gabai. דידך לרשות
הרבים מפיק. Didach l'reshus harabbim mafik. Yours is going into the רשות
הרבים. reshus harabbim. מאן מחיל גבך, Man machil gabach, who's מוחל mocheil
for you? Their silence does not give you rights. And now they're
complaining. רבי ינאי, Rebbi Yannai, now we're going to have another story
which will be a... yeah...
when the גמרא Gemara starts what is this one little phrase והאידנא
וזימנין דמפיק ולא ידעתי? ve'hadinan ve'zimnin de-mapik v'la yadati?
Sometimes the ceiling will
collapse or will crack and nobody's paying attention. That's about the tunnel
under the רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim.
Oh, the response to that רישא, reisha, to that...
yeah... like why isn't it enough that you can have a wagon
with... okay. רבי ינאי. Rebbi Yannai. רבי ינאי הוה ליה אילן נוטה
לרשות הרבים. Rebbi Yannai hava lei ilan noteh l'reshus harabbim. רבי ינאי
Rebbi Yannai had
a tree that overhung רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. הוה ההוא גברא דהוה
ליה נמי אילן נוטה לרשות הרבים. Hava hu gavra d'hava lei nami
ilan noteh l'reshus harabbim. Now it's an exact parallel. Somebody else had
a tree that overhung רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. אתו בני רשות הרבים
וקא מעכבי עילויה. Atu benei reshus harabbim ve'ka me-akevei ilei.
So the people of רשות הרבים reshus harabbim were starting to complain
to this guy that his tree overhang רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. So
אתא לקמיה דרבי ינאי. ata l'kamei d'Rebbi Yannai. Now אתא ata is
in the singular. So it seems to me that the people here
are smart... are choosing their venue intentionally. Okay. So this guy that's
being sued by the בני רשות הרבים, benei reshus harabbim, he says,
"Okay let's go to רבי ינאי." Rebbi Yannai. Okay, רבי ינאי Rebbi
Yannai excuse me, knowing that רבי ינאי Rebbi Yannai similarly had a
tree. So אתא קמיה דרבי ינאי. ata kamei d'Rebbi Yannai. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, so רבי ינאי Rebbi Yannai said to him, זיל האידנא
ותא למחר. Zil idna v'ta lamachar. You know what? I'm a little
busy today. Come see me tomorrow. Okay. Because רבי ינאי Rebbi Yannai
could obviously anticipate what the... was going to happen. So בליליא, belailya,
that night, שדר קצייה לההוא דידיה. shadar katsei l'hau didei.
He went and he hired somebody to cut down his tree that
night. Okay. אתא לקמיה. Ata l'kamei. So then the next morning the
guy came to him. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said to
the guy, זיל קוץ, zil kots, go cut down your tree. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, ומר נמי אית ליה, v'mar nami is lei, what
do you mean? You also have a tree overhanging רשות הרבים. reshus
harabbim. אמר ליה, Amar lei, זיל חזי, zil chazei, let's go see.
אי קאיץ דידי קוץ דידך, Ei ka-its didi, kots didach, if my
tree is cut down, you cut down your tree. ואי לא קאיץ
דידי לא תקוץ, V'i lo ka-its didi, lo tikots, and if my
tree isn't cut down, you don't have to cut down yours. Fine.
You'll do exactly what I do. Let's go see what the story
is with mine. Okay. And obviously his had been cut down. So
now the גמרא Gemara says, "Alright that's all very nice, but what
was רבי ינאי Rebbi Yannai doing with a tree overhanging רשות הרבים?"
reshus harabbim? You're not supposed to be impeding the רשות הרבים, reshus
harabbim, right? And it gets in the way of their camels and
of people walking and so on. So מעיקרא מאי סבר ולבסוף מאי
סבר. me'ikara mai savar v'lisof mai savar. So what... what was he
thinking initially, רבי ינאי, Rebbi Yannai, that he allowed this tree to
grow in... overhang רשות הרבים? reshus harabbim? No. מעיקרא סבר Me'ikara savar
originally he thought ניחא להו לבני רשות הרבים דיתבי בטולה. nichu l'hu
livnei reshus harabbim d'yasvi b'tula. That his... you know, he assumed that
the people would prefer this. Have nice shaded walkway. Okay. So you
know you have to duck a little bit when you get to
the tree. But he assumed
that...
then he saw that they were complaining against this other guy and
he realized oh so they really don't like it so the reason
they haven't said anything to me has something to do with the
fact that I'm Rav Yannai not have to do with the fact
they really like the fact that there's a tree okay so כיון
דחזא דקא מעכבי Keivan De-Chaza De-Kamaachvi שדא וקצייה Shada V'Katzya so
then he cut it down he realized that the only reason they
hadn't complained to him was out of deference to him but they
really did not like the fact that there was a tree in
רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim okay so ולימא ליה זיל קוץ דידך והדר
אקוץ דידי V'Leima Lei Zil Kotz Didach V'Hadar Ekotz Didi so why'd
he have to do this sneaky thing and buy himself a day
and cut it down at night why didn't he say cut down
yours and then he'll say oh yours isn't cut down he'd say
yeah I just now realized that רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim doesn't want
it I'm going to cut down mine right you know after we're
done here today why did he have to go ahead and do
his own thing first so משום דריש לקיש Mishum D'Reish Lakish because
it's the principle that ריש לקיש Reish Lakish teaches דאמר ריש לקיש
D'Amar Reish Lakish says התקוששו וקושו Hitkosheshu V'Kosho so I don't exactly
know the I know the גמרא Gemara translation that word I don't
know the literal translation of that verse but anyway like קש Kash
is like the way the רשב"ם Rashbam says it it'd have to
be like gathering straw or removing straw but the דרשה Drasha is
the following התפעל Hitpa'el התפעל Hitpa'el is the reflective form of the
verb so it says קשוט Kashot it's a play on the words
not קש Kash of straw but קשוט Kashot beautify yourself קשוט עצמך
Kashot Atzmecha first התקוששו Hitkosheshu do reflective ואחר קשוט אחרים V'Achar Kashot
Acheirim and then tell other people what you know what they have
to do to look nice don't go ahead and you know give
advice or criticize somebody unless you've taken care of it for yourself
first you know so the רשב"ם Rashbam actually says something which to
me has a echo in some other religious text other religions text
he says the רשב"ם Rashbam says התקוששו הסר קש מבין עיניך
תחלה
Hitkosheshu Haseir Kash Mibein Einecha
Techila לקושש קש Lekoshish Kash right that's what I was referring to
I know I know what does it remove the beam from your
eyes don't
remove the splinter from your fellow's
eye
before you remove the beam from your eyes from your own eye
exactly there you go
that's a person that didn't spring that's powerful
yeah right right so before you go start make sure like you
are your hands are clean before you start telling other people how
they're supposed to act okay
so go overnight what how clean is that to go overnight
right but before he actually no he look his was an innocent
mistake he hadn't done a he hadn't intentionally done something wrong but
before he was going to tell somebody to correct themselves he wanted
to make sure he had cleaned up his own act right so
he hadn't done anything wrong but I mean it's a beautiful point
right you know so okay אבל אם רצה כנס את שלו מוציא
Aval Im Ratza Konas Et Shelo Motzi
now
if you want to though you bring it inside and then you
you know you go back from your property line oh my God
I forgot to finish this off okay איבעיא להו Ibaya Lehu they
said כנס ולא הוציא מהו שיחזור ויוציא Konas V'Lo Hotzi Mahu Sheyachzor
V'Yotzi let's say you put back your wall and with the intention
to have these protrusions and then in the end you decided you're
not going to have the protrusions or you'd rather have the wall
go up to the property line when you move the wall back
have you already waived the space to רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim or
in the end of the day it's still your space and you
can still put it back to the property line so כנס ולא
הוציא Konas V'Lo Hotzi
I'm sorry I jumped ahead in the גמרא Gemara the first question
is no no no first you moved it back and you went
a few months without doing anything and now you want to put
out the protrusions so can we say that you're waiting and not
putting out the protrusions basically you've waived your right to put out
the protrusions and you've basically like just given the space to רשות
הרבים Reshus HaRabim so what's the story רבי יוחנן אומר כנס ומוציא
Rabbi Yochanan Omer Konas U-Motzi no no no even after
you've put the wall inside and you know waited a period of
time you can still later put out the protrusions it's still your
property וריש לקיש אומר כנס אינו מוציא V'Reish Lakish Omer Konas Eino
Motzi no no no it all has to be done at once
and if you've moved your wall back and haven't done anything for
a while then the space becomes רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim and you
have lost your rights אמר ליה רבי יעקב לרבי ירמיה בר תחליפא
Amar Lei Rabbi Yaakov L'Rabbi Yirmiyah Bar Tachlifa so Rabbi Yaakov said
to רבי ירמיה בר תחליפא Rabbi Yirmiyah Bar Tachlifa אסברא לך Asberach
Lach let me let me explain to you my understanding of this
debate להוציא כולי עלמא לא פליגי דמוציא L'Hotzi Kulei Alma Lo Pleigi
D'Motzi everybody agrees that if you moved your wall back with the
intent to put out the protrusions you can put out those protrusions
at a later time okay obviously that's why you did it it's
still your property that's not a problem okay כי פליגי Ki Pleigi
what's the debate להחזיר כתלים למקומן L'Hachzir Ktalim Limkomon so this I
had jumped ahead if you now actually don't want to have it
as you know as protrusions with your wall back you actually want
to fully reclaim the space and move the wall back to the
original place
having done the protrusions already yes or no either way
okay ואיפכא איתמר V'Ippcha Itmar it was said the opposite רבי יוחנן
אומר אינו
מחזיר Rabbi Yochanan Omer Eino Machzir רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan here's the
one that's strict you cannot restore the wall to its original place
וריש לקיש אומר מחזיר V'Reish Lakish Omer Machzir you can now what's
the logic רבי יוחנן אינו מחזיר Rabbi Yochanan Eino Machzir משום דרבי
יהודה Mishum D'Rabbi Yehuda that he would think if you have rights
to put the protrusions out there it's still your space so why
can't you reclaim it and move the wall back because of רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda דאמר רבי יהודה מצר שהחזיקו בו רבים אסור לקלקלו
d'amar Rabbi Yehuda meitzar shehecheziku bo rabbim assur l'kalkelo that
a path that the רבים rabbim have taken possession of, even if
it's your property, you cannot go ahead and destroy it. The boundary?
No,
it means here a path. If you look at the רשב״ם, Rashbam,
yeah, you look at the רשב״ם, Rashbam, he says מצר שבין שתי
שדות שהחזיקו בו. meitzar shebein shtei sadot shehecheziku bo. I mean, what,
I don't
know, how did they translate it?
The context is you move the wall back and the boundary to
רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim.
Interesting.
How do they translate it there in the English?
Let me see.
It's okay.
Oh, okay, which the public established a right of way. Okay, you're
right. He translates the word the same as you, but the context
is you have a boundary but they've been walking on the boundary.
Okay, so but you're right, the word מצר meitzar is a boundary.
Right, it's a boundary, but the החזיקו בו hecheziku bo means they
have basically established passage through, over your boundary. Right, but you're right,
the word מצר meitzar is boundary.
Call it a public thoroughfare. A public, okay,
good.
So, okay, מצר שהחזיקו בו רבים. meitzar shehecheziku bo rabbim. So if
they're now walking on your boundary line, אסור לקלקלו, assur l'kalkelo, and
they've, they've established that and through their practice, you cannot go ahead
and destroy it. So the point being, yes, you moved your wall
back. Technically this is still your property. And the proof is you're
allowed to put the protrusions out there. But it's still, but they
also have a right of passage. So now you've got a reality
that because it's your property you retain the right to have the
protrusions, but because they've been walking on it they have a right
of passage. So you cannot put your wall back and take away
the right of passage. You still can have the protrusions, it's still
your property, but you cannot take away the right of passage. חליפה.
chalifa. Where do we have חליפה? chalifa?
It's the name, but doesn't it mean it's changed?
Oh yeah, but here it's exchanged,
interesting. Okay, let me just finish this. וריש לקיש אמר מחזיר. v'Reish
Lakish amar machzir. He says no, you can put your wall back.
הני מילי היכא דליכא רווחא. hani mili heicha d'leika revacha. When is
it that you cannot take back a path that they have sort
of established on your property line? That's when you're not giving them
any other passageway. There's no space that's left over. They basically have
been cutting through your backyard and now you're going to stop them
from cutting through your backyard. Well, they have no way of passage
without that. הכא איכא רווחא. hacha ika revacha. Here you'll take back
your thing and you still have the whole רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim.
You're just taking back your space, but you're not preventing them from
the basic passage. So therefore it is allowed to reestablish. You had
a question Jonathan? Okay.
The protrusions are still going to get in the way.
I know. So it's an interesting thing. You can't stop them from
going through, but you are still allowed to, your property rights still
do entitle you to those protrusions. Right. Okay, let's finish up. לקח
חצר והיו בה זיזין וגזוזטראות הרי זו בחזקתה. lakach chatzer v'hayu bah
zizin v'gazuztraot harei zo b'chezkatah. So if you bought this חצר chatzer
and it has these protrusions, you can assume everything is okay and
you're allowed to keep them. אמר רב הונא נפלה חוזר ובונה אותה.
amar Rav Huna nafla chozer u'voneh otah. If it fell down you
can rebuild it because the same way when you bought it you
assumed it was there legally, even if you have to rebuild it
you can assume you have the legal rights. So the גמרא Gemara
says מיתיבי. meitivei. Asked on that, אין מסיידין ואין מכיירין ואין מפייחין
בזמן הזה. ein mesaydin v'ein mechayrin v'ein mefaychin bazman hazeh.
You cannot go ahead when you're building a house, this is all
זכר לחורבן, zecher l'churban, and go ahead and put beautiful plaster, nice
clean plaster on your walls. מכיירין mechayrin either is carvings, drawings on
the walls, or it's another type of plaster. Okay, so you cannot
do these plasterings of your walls or do illustrations on your walls,
זכר לחורבן zecher l'churban nowadays. A fresco.
A fresco. לקח חצר מסוידת מכוירת מפויחת, lakach chatzer mesuyedet mechuyeret mefuyachet,
however if you bought a courtyard that already had this type of
plaster on it, הרי זו בחזקתה. harei zo b'chezkatah. You don't have
to destroy it, you're allowed to keep it. נפלה, nafla, if it
fell down, אינו חוזר ובונה אותה. eino chozer u'voneh otah. Now you're
rebuilding it, you can't rebuild it and do the plastering again. So
you see there's a difference between rebuilding, allowing you to keep it,
and rebuilding it. So the גמרא Gemara says no, איסורא שאני. issura
shani. That's different. That is for the sake of זכר לחורבן, zecher
l'churban, so when you build something, now you're building it new, you
can't do it beautiful. You have to have a little זכר לחורבן.
zecher l'churban. Okay, but here it's a question about monetary rights. I
have property rights to this. I should assume this is my property
and that these protrusions are on my property. So even if it
fell down, I retain those property rights. תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. Now
we're going to go focus on this זכר לחורבן. zecher l'churban.
How
hard has it been used as a phrase explicitly?
I know. It just says בזמן הזה. bazman hazeh. But now we're
going to directly address it. Okay, and we have two minutes, so
no questions. לא יסוד אדם את ביתו בסיד. lo yasud adam et
beito b'sid. Do not go ahead and put nice plaster on your
house, white clean plaster. ואם עירב בו חול או תבן מותר. v'im
erev bo chol o teven mutar. But if you mix sand or
straw, then it's not so nice and bright white, it's a little
grayer, that's okay. רבי יהודה אומר עירב בו חול הרי זה תרסיד.
Rabbi Yehuda omer erev bo chol harei zeh tarsid. No, if you
put sand that makes it like cement, that actually makes it. better
and you're not allowed to do that. ואסור. Va'asur. תבן, Teven, if
you put straw, מותר, Mutar, that just makes it a duller color
and that's okay, then it's not as much, it's not as beautiful.
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
When the second בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash was destroyed, רבו פרושים בישראל.
rabu prushim be'Yisrael. There were many, not Pharisees, there were many ascetics
amongst the Jewish people, people that were sort of denied themselves physical
pleasure. שלא לאכול בשר ושלא לשתות יין, Shelo le'echol basar veshelo lishtos
yayin, that they're not going to eat meat or drink wine. נטפל
להן רבי יהושע. Nitpal lahen Rabbi Yehoshua. Rabbi Yehoshua sort of was
assigned to them, you know, or attended to them. אמר להן, Amar
lahen, and he said to them, בני, banai, my sons, מפני מה
אי אתם אוכלין בשר ואין אתם שותין יין? mipney mah i-atem ochlin
basar ve'ein atem shosin yayin? Why have you adopted this religious practice?
אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said to him, נאכל בשר שממנו מקריבין
על גבי מזבח ועכשיו בטל? nochal basar shemimmennu makrivin al gabey hamizbe'ach
ve'achshav batel? Should we eat meat that they used to bring it
on the altar, and now there's no altar? נשתה יין שמנסכין על
גבי המזבח ועכשיו בטל? Nishteh yayin shemanaschin al gabey hamizbe'ach ve'achshav batel?
Should we drink wine that they used to use it for the
holiest religious purpose? So basically they were living their lives זכר לחורבן.
zecher lachurban. Like every—the every day was the Nine Days, okay? Actually
some say that this is maybe the source of some of those
מנהגים minhagim of, you know, the Nine Days was that okay, for
Nine Days we'll have these זכר לחורבן. zecher lachurban. They were doing
it their whole lives, okay, with this direct connection to the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay. אמר
להן, Amar lahen, he said, אם כן לחם נמי לא נאכל. im
ken lechem nami lo nochal. Let's do a reductio ad absurdum here.
לחם לא נאכל, Lechem lo nochal, let's not eat bread, שכבר בטלו
מנחות? shekvar batlu menachos? We don't bring a מנחה mincha which is
made out of wheat and you know, flour and water. So they
said, okay, אפשר בפירות. efshar bepeiros. Fine, we won't eat bread, we'll
just have fruit. You know, one person's reductio ad absurdum is another
person's אי הכי נמי. ein hachi nami. Anyway, פירות לא נאכל? peiros
lo nochal? He said no, you can't eat fruit, שכבר בטלו ביכורים?
shekvar batlu bikkurim? We're no longer bringing the ביכורים. bikkurim. Oh, אפשר
בפירות אחרים—no, efshar bepeiros acherim that was only from the שבעת המינים.
shivas haminim. It's okay,
we'll eat other fruit. Fine, we'll go with that. Good idea. We
won't eat that, we won't eat that, we could still survive. So
then he got to them, no, מים לא נשתה? mayim lo nishteh?
Ah, you can't drink water, שכבר בטל ניסוך המים, shekvar batul nisuch
hamayim, because you don't do the anointing—the pour—libations of water on
סוכות. Sukkos. שתקו. Shatku. That they didn't have an answer. How are
they going to survive without water? Of course תוספות Tosafos says, I
don't understand, what about like fruit juice? But okay, let's keep on
going. Okay.
So אמר להן, amar lahen, he said to them, בני באו ואומר
לכם, banai bo'u ve'omar lachem, let me go—let me explain this to
you. שלא להתאבל כל עיקר אי אפשר, Shelo le'isabel kol ikkar i
efshar, not to mourn at all, that's not an option. שכבר נגזרה
גזרה, Shekvar nigzera gezera, the decree has been given, the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash is destroyed, we have to recognize that, we have to
have a degree of mourning. ולהתאבל יותר מדאי אי אפשר, U'le'isabel yoser
midai i efshar, but to be overly immersed in mourning,
that you can't. שאין גוזרין גזרה על הציבור אלא אם כן רוב
הציבור יכולים לעמוד בה, She'ein gozrin gezera al hatzibbur ela im ken
rov hatzibbur yecholin la'amod bah, it has to be something that the
community can tolerate, דכתיב, dechtiv, במארה אתם נארים ואותי אתם קובעים הגוי
כולו. bim'eira atem ne'arim ve'oti atem kovim hagoy kullo. So this is
a whole big פסוק pasuk to unpack, but it basically means you've
adopted this curse upon yourselves that if you don't give מעשר, ma'aser,
anyway in this sort of thing you did הגוי כולו, hagoy kullo,
the
entire nation adopted this edict or this curse. So it has to
be something the whole nation can accept. Of course the irony here
is that they weren't trying to establish it on the whole nation.
It was רבו פרושים, rabu prushim, right, they were ascetics, they were
a special group. So he said, okay, let everybody do what they'll
do, we're going to do our own thing. But I think his
basic point was was no, don't separate yourself out from the community.
Like if this isn't right for the community like you have to
sort of get on with your lives and normalize your practice and
not live a practice that's like separated from the way most people
have to be able to live their lives. But again it is
ironic because they weren't trying to demand other people, they were just
accepting a practice for themselves. Okay. So what do you do? אלא
כך אמרו חכמים. Ela kach amru chachamim. This is the right balance.
סד אדם את ביתו בסיד. Sad adam et beto besid. You can
plaster your house. ומשייר בו דבר מועט. U'meshayer bo davar mu'at. You
leave over a little space that's unplastered. וכמה, Ve'kamah, how much? אמר
רב יוסף אמה על אמה. Amar Rav Yosef ama al ama. One
like אמה ama by an אמה, ama, you know, whatever it is,
a foot and a half by a foot and a half that
you don't plaster. אמר רב חסדא כנגד הפתח, Amar Rav Chisda keneged
hapetach, and it should be very visible, opposite the doorway. עושה אדם
כל צורכי סעודה. Oseh adam kol tzorkey se'udah. You can eat as
much as you want, have as much food as you want in
a meal. ומשייר דבר מועט בו. U'meshayer davar mu'at bo. But leave
over a little bit, don't eat everything. מאי היא, Mai hi, what
would be the little thing you'd leave over? אמר רב פפא כסא
דהרסנא, Amar Rav Papa kassa deharsana, like a little fish hash. Just
leave a little something over זכר לחורבן. zecher lachurban. עושה אשה כל
תכשיטיה. Oseh isha kol tachshiteha. A woman should put on as much
jewelry as she wants. ומשיירת דבר מועט. U'meshaeres davar mu'at. But put
a little bit she doesn't do. A little like makeup and jewelry.
מאי היא, Mai hi, אמר רב בת צידה, amar Rav bat tsida,
like the temples, not to I guess put some rouge or whatever
on her temples. שנאמר אם אשכחך ירושלים, Shenne'emar im eshkachech Yerushalayim,
this is not just on the אשה, isha, this is on everything,
תשכח ימיני תדבק לשוני לחכי אם לא אזכרכי, tishkach yemini tidbak leshoni
lechikki im lo ezkerechi,
right? So this is—now it's funny because obviously that was the whole
context, like—but he's trying to say a more moderate approach. Yes, we
have to remember ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Maybe his point is that the fact
that we need things to serve to spark our—to force us to
remember, אם אשכחך, im eshkachech, means that we're not constantly indulged in
this, you know, mourning. Like we get on with our lives and
lives, but we make sure that we don't forget. And that's the
right balance. Alright, מאי על ראש שמחתי, Mai Al Rosh Simchati, I'll
bring ירושלים Yerushalayim at the top of all my rejoicing. אמר רב
יצחק: Amar Rav Yitzchak: זה Zeh אפר מקלה שבראש חתנים. eifer mikleh
she-berosh chatanim. That's some like ashes that you put at the heads
of the grooms. So even at the time of greatest joy at
a wedding, and the ראש rosh literally the head, you put it
at the head of the joy and you remember ירושלים, Yerushalayim, which
is why we sing the song at the end of a wedding.
Okay, אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי: Amar lei Rav Pappa le-Abaye: היכא
מנח לה? Heicha manach lah? Where do you put the ashes? במקום
תפילין, Bimkom Tefillin, where the תפילין Tefillin would go, שנאמר: shenemar: לשום
לאבלי ציון לתת להם פאר תחת אפר. lasum le-aveilei Tziyon latet lahem
pe'er tachat eifer. For the mourners of Zion, that they should have
that in their future they will have glory where there were ashes.
And the תפילין Tefillin are called glory, so it means that now
the ashes are where the glory would be. The ashes are where
the תפילין Tefillin would be, so it's sort of remembering this mourning
even at the time of greatest joy. Of course the irony is,
is that you break the glass
as a זכר לחורבן zecher le-churban and then everybody yells מזל טוב.
mazal tov. But okay. וכל המתאבל על ירושלים, Ve-chol ha-mitabel al Yerushalayim,
anybody that mourns for Jerusalem, זוכה ורואה בשמחתה, zoheh ve-roeh be-simchatah, eventually
because you participate in this mourning, you will see in the rejoicing,
שנאמר: shenemar: שמחו את ירושלים וגילו בה כל אוהביה שישו אתה משוש
כל המתאבלים עליה. Simchu et Yerushalayim ve-gilu vah kol ohaveha sisu itah
masos kol ha-mitablim aleha. Right, so you'll rejoice all those that now
are mourning for it. תניא אמר רבי ישמעאל בן אלישע: Tanya Amar
Rabbi Yishmael ben Elisha: מיום שחרב בית המקדש, mi-yom she-charav Beit Ha-Mikdash,
דין הוא שנגזור על עצמנו—now din hu she-nigzor al atzmenu the גמרא
Gemara pushes back, like really, what we're doing is, we really should
be stricter. In principle, we should accept upon ourselves שלא לאכול בשר
ושלא לשתות יין. she-lo le'echol basar ve-she-lo lishtot yayin. אלא אין גוזרין
גזירה על הצבור אלא אם כן רוב הצבור יכולין לעמוד בה. Ela
ein gozrin gezeirah al ha-tzibbur ela im ken rov ha-tzibbur yecholin la'amod
bah. So it's interesting, like here saying we really should be doing
this, but you know what, we can't manage it. ומיום שפשטה מלכות
הרשעה שגוזרת עלינו גזירות רעות, U-mi-yom she-pashtah malchut ha-risha'ah she-gozeret aleinu gezeirot
ra'ot,
and from the time the evil government, meaning the Romans, have now
made these edicts against us, ומבטלת ממנו תורה, u-mevatala mimenu Torah, and
they prevent us from learning Torah, this must have been the time
of, you know, the real persecutions, ומצות, u-mitzvot, ואין מנחת אותנו ליכנס
לשבוע הבן, ve-ein manachat otanu likanes le-shavua ha-ben, לשבוע הבן, le-shavua ha-ben,
the רשב"ם Rashbam says it means a ברית מילה, bris milah, they
don't let us have a ברית מילה. bris milah. ואמרי לה לישוע
הבן, Ve-amrei lah le-yeshua ha-ben, which is maybe just a different way
of referring to it. So we can't learn תורה Torah and do
ברית מילה, bris milah, so we're really under these terrible edicts. It's
not just זכר לחורבן. zecher le-churban. He says, דין הוא שנגזור על
עצמנו שלא לישא אשה ושלא להוליד בנים. din hu she-nigzor al atzmenu
she-lo lisa isha ve-she-lo leholid banim. This sort of is like the
מדרשים, Midrashim, you know, that עמרם Amram said, we're not going to
have any children with גזירת פרעה, gezeirat Paroh, and מרים Miriam had
to say no, that's a worse edict than פרעה's. Paroh But here
the גמרא Gemara seems to be endorsing that. Really, if we can't
do a ברית מילה bris milah and we can't learn תורה Torah
and our kids aren't going to grow up to be able to
do מצוות, mitzvot, maybe we shouldn't just have kids. Of course that
would be a worse consequence, then you're ensuring that there's going to
be no future generation. ונמצא זרעו של אברהם כלה מאליו. Ve-nimtza zaro
shel Avraham kaleh me-eilav. Let's just let it happen by itself, that
there won't be any Jews rather than have Jews not do מצוות,
mitzvot, which is like what? Why is that a better option? That's
very bizarre, the idea that that's what we should be doing. אלא
הניחו להם לישראל מוטב שיהיו שוגגין ואל יהיו מזידין. Ela hanichu lahem
le-Yisrael mutav she-yihyu shogegin ve-al yihyu mezidin. But you know what? People
feel they have to get married and who are we to tell
them not to get married? They won't listen to us anyway. So
we'll let them go ahead. This is very ironic, right? Because that
seems like much worse advice. It seems like מרים Miriam knew what
she was talking about according to that מדרש. Midrash. How is this
better than having kids and ensuring the next generation, you know, which
might do better than this generation? So it's a very strange end
of this פרק, perek, but anyway raises, you know, important issues about
what is the right way of balancing like זכר לחורבן zecher le-churban
and getting on with your lives and dealing with these types of
challenges. So we will begin the next פרק. perek.